<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>C | Anurag Roy</title>
    <link>https://ranarag.github.io/tag/c/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ranarag.github.io/tag/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>C</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 20:19:01 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ranarag.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>C</title>
      <link>https://ranarag.github.io/tag/c/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>From CPP to Java</title>
      <link>https://ranarag.github.io/post/cpp_to_java/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 12:01:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ranarag.github.io/post/cpp_to_java/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some differences between c++ and java:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java compiled code is platform independent whereas c++ compiled code is
platform dependent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java interpreter reports the run-time error that caused the execution to halt
unlike in c/c++ programs which may simply crash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;c/c++ do not have strict sizes for the fundamental datatypes(varies from
machine to machine) whereas Java defines strict sizes for their datatypes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java has additional positive and negative zeros, positive and neagtive infinites and &amp;ldquo;nan&amp;rdquo;(not a number values)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;c/c++ has functions while Java has methods.In c/c++ functions can be defined outside a class
Java doesnot allow methods to be defined outside a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike c++  arrays, Java arrays are objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike c++, strings are immutable in Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in c++ classes &amp;ldquo;public&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;private&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;protected&amp;rdquo; are labels , in Java they are modifiers. Each member has its own access modifier. Java also has a no-modifier(a.k.a package-private) option which makes
the member visible only within its own package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike c++, Java method definitions do not have
semicolon at the end of their closing brackets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java uses the &amp;ldquo;extends&amp;rdquo; keyword while inherting features of a class to specify the superclass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.programmerinterview.com/index.php/java-questions/multiple-inheritance/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;does not support multiple inheritance but supports multiple interfaces&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike c++ Java has 
&lt;a href=&#34;www.javatpoint.com/difference-between-abstract-class-and-interface&#34;&gt;interfaces which is a bit different from abstract class&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Java superclass constructors are callled using the keyword &amp;ldquo;super&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike c++ Java has class hierarchy. The  &amp;ldquo;Object&amp;rdquo; class is the root of this hierarchy.
All classes are subclasses of this root class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;there-are-many-other-differences-also-but-these-basic-differences-will-help-you-get-your-hands-dirty-with-java--&#34;&gt;There are many other differences also but these basic differences will help you get your hands dirty with Java !! :)&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Guidelines</title>
      <link>https://ranarag.github.io/post/programming_guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2016 10:04:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ranarag.github.io/post/programming_guidelines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://spinroot.com/gerard/pdf/P10.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Power of Ten-Rules for Developing Safety Critical Code&lt;/a&gt;
the author has stated 10 rules adhering to which will make one a good programmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author chosed C as the language for writing safety critical code because of the extensive tool support for this language including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strong source code analyzers like 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://valgrind.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;valgrind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;debuggers like gdb&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;stable compilers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test support tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following are the 10 rules the author wants to emphasize upon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: Restrict all code to very simple control flow constructs – do not use goto
statements, setjmp or longjmp constructs, and direct or indirect recursion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author says to restrict all code to very simple control flow constructs because
it enhances code clarity. Now asking not to use recursion might look suprising but
this is also used to improve code clarity.(Remember that every recursive solution has an
equivalent iterative solution.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: All loops must have a fixed upper-bound. It must be trivially possible for a
checking tool to prove statically that a preset upper-bound on the number of iterations
of a loop cannot be exceeded. If the loop-bound cannot be proven statically, the rule
is considered violated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this rule does not need any explanations except for the fact that this rule is not applicable to iterations that
are non-terminating(e.g. in a  process scheduler).In those cases we need to statistically prove that no upper-bound exists for such a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: Do not use dynamic memory allocation after initialization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is given because memory allocators and garbage collectors often have unpredictable behaviour which might cause a coding error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: No function should be longer than what can be printed on a single sheet of
paper in a standard reference format with one line per statement and one line per
declaration. Typically, this means no more than about 60 lines of code per function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is given to ensure modularity and enhance readability. The author states in his rationale
that &amp;ldquo;excessively long functions are often a sign of poorly structured code.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: The assertion density of the code should average to a minimum of two
assertions per function. Assertions are used to check for anomalous conditions that
should never happen in real-life executions. Assertions must always be side-effect
free and should be defined as Boolean tests. When an assertion fails, an explicit
recovery action must be taken, e.g., by returning an error condition to the caller of the
function that executes the failing assertion. Any assertion for which a static checking
tool can prove that it can never fail or never hold violates this rule. (I.e., it is not
possible to satisfy the rule by adding unhelpful “assert(true)” statements.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because assertions make it easier to find bugs in the code.They are also &amp;ldquo;side effect free&amp;rdquo;
which means that they can be selectively disabled without changing the behaviour of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: Data objects must be declared at the smallest possible level of scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule uses the principle of data hiding. Many errors occur in programs because of wrong referencing
of objects in the code. So if we reduce the scope of refer the object we will be able to find mistake in
referencing in a lesser amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: The return value of non-void functions must be checked by each calling
function, and the validity of parameters must be checked inside each function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the author this is one of the most important rule because sometimes return value of a function
helps us to find error in the code.For e.g. lets say we have problem in closing a file in C.We can do two things
here:
1. The time consuming one - Put various printf and assertion statements trying to find where
he error is occurring.
2. The time saving one - Check the return value of the function close() and lookup it&amp;rsquo;s errno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: The use of the preprocessor must be limited to the inclusion of header files and
simple macro definitions. Token pasting, variable argument lists (ellipses), and
recursive macro calls are not allowed. All macros must expand into complete
syntactic units. The use of conditional compilation directives is often also dubious,
but cannot always be avoided. This means that there should rarely be justification for
more than one or two conditional compilation directives even in large software
development efforts, beyond the standard boilerplate that avoids multiple inclusion of
the same header file. Each such use should be flagged by a tool-based checker and
justified in the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule: The use of pointers should be restricted. Specifically, no more than one level of
dereferencing is allowed. Pointer dereference operations may not be hidden in macro
definitions or inside typedef declarations. Function pointers are not permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pointers often make codes hard to analyze especially by static analyzers.As the author says
&amp;quot; Function pointers, can seriously restrict the types of checks that can be performed
by static analyzers and should only be used if there is a strong justification for their use,
and ideally alternate means are provided to assist tool-based checkers determine flow of
control and function call hierarchies&amp;rdquo;.Function pointers make it impossible for a tool to
prove absence of recursion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; Rule: All code must be compiled, from the first day of development, with all
&amp;gt; compiler warnings enabled at the compiler’s most pedantic setting. All code must
&amp;gt; compile with these setting without any warnings. All code must be checked daily with
&amp;gt; at least one, but preferably more than one, state-of-the-art static source code analyzer
&amp;gt; and should pass the analyses with zero warnings.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
